[Jeenio]
All right guys, here we go!
I give you Buu342, with the seminar!
[Buu342]
All right, hello everyone and welcome to my little seminar
on Nintendo 64 homebrew game development.
The original intention was to do this
on the console itself,
but due to issues with the
hardware that I bought
to get it from RCA (A/V) to HDMI,
it was exactly what I paid... So...
The quality... Fantastic...
So instead we're going to be doing
this seminar on an emulator
which is not as good...
But, I mean, it's better than
having no seminar.
Just in case, I have prepared a
PowerPoint backup
And if my computer decides to
completely die,
then I also have an interpretive dance.
Anyway, let's go into the wonderful,
wonderful world
of Nintendo 64 homebrew development.
First, a very brief introduction.
My name is Lourenço Soares,
although you might know me more
by the name: Buu342
Pronounce that however you
want, that can be
B U U three four two,
Buu three hundred forty two...
Whatever is more fun for you!
I'm a computer science student,
I started Nintendo 64 development
more or less around early 2018.
I'm mostly known for a little project
of mine involving a little bird.
Since then, I've been trying to improve
the general development scene
I've made tools, I've written guides...
I've even released a multi-part series
describing the development of
the little bird project.
I've written USB debugging libraries,
texture converters,
and most recently I've released
an animation plug-in and library for
Blender
that allows you to have
fully animated models on the N64
without much trouble.
I do open source everything that I do.
Literally everything!
Thankfully, working on a Nintendo 64 game
It's a lot more accessible now,
and that's generally my idea.
But... The key word there is: "accessible",
not necessarily easier...
Because you see...
the Nintendo 64 was quite difficult.
So much so, that the
hardware development chief at the time,
Genyo Takeda, he referred to the system's
programming challenges by the word
Hansei (反省)
Which means "reflective regret".
(Hence, the name of this presentation)
It's probably not as hard as something like
the PlayStation 2,
which has 10 different processors...
Or the Sega Saturn, which instead of using
triangles it uses quadrilateral meshes,
it has insanely tight timings between
its eight processors
It's a mess...
But, I mean, it's very challenging for
someone who's never done
embedded systems development before.
And it's kind of been getting harder
and easier as time has gone on...
We'll get into that a little bit
better later...
Frankly, honestly, I think there'd be
an alternate universe
where instead of me giving
you this seminar,
I'd instead be giving you this:
But anyway, let's talk about
why this is the case,
the challenges that all developers (and
you, if you're interested in N64
development) will have to face,
the history, and the future...
And obviously, you're going to
be getting this seminar
from someone who not only
drank the Kool-Aid,
but is also actively helping produce it.
So after that little intro,
you're kinda wondering
*why* on earth anyone would want
to do this to themselves?
Well, first of all, the N64 is
kind of in that time where
you can make an entire game by yourself
in a reasonable time frame, and not
have it look too out of place, because
the games aren't super graphically complex.
There's absolutely no assembly
experience required.
It helps for debugging or
disassembling your code,
but it is not needed at all.
You don't really need any special hardware
or anything,
you just need to get a flashcart.
Or just don't...
But trust me, get a flashcart...
And getting an N64 is like 70$ on eBay,
with a controller.
So, y'know, it's relatively cheap.
And honestly, it feels awesome to get
your code running on the system
I think anyone that's ever done
any sort of homebrew
will agree with that.
So, first let's talk about the hardware
It's a little bit boring, I'm sorry,
but it's kind of a necessary evil...
The hardware was designed by
Silicon Graphics,
which were the leaders of
computer graphics at the time.
It was very ahead of its curve,
retailing at 250$.
Now, I could spend years talking about
ever little minute detail of the N64,
because the community has done
a fantastic job of
reverse engineering protocols,
decapping chips...
But today, I'm going to be focusing
on the three main components
that the programmers only
need to worry about.
and that is: the father,
the son,
and the holy ghost.
So, the CPU, it's a derivative of a
MIPS R4300i,
it has some slightly modified
pin outs and clock rate.
It runs at 93.75 megahertz,
has a 16 kilobyte instruction cache.
It's relatively good at doing
floating point arithmetic.
In fact it's actually faster
than fixed point arithmetic.
It's 64-bit, hence why it was called
the Nintendo 64.
But the system bus is 32 bits wide,
so games are designed with
32-Bit calling conventions
to maximize performance.
So the whole 64 thing is
kind of marketing junk,
but, you know, at the same time
it's also not...
I wanted to get some GoldenEye music
for this, but I didn't have time to
setup audio...
So the RAM is 250 megahertz
Rambus DRAM, or RDRAM for short.
It's 4 megabytes, split into
1 megabyte banks.
But it's actually 4.5 megabytes
because it's actually 9 bit RAM.
The 9th bit is used for anti-aliasing
and Z-buffering by the RCP,
but it's not exposed to the programmer,
so he doesn't need to worry about it.
The data bus is 8 bits
(9 bits, obviously).
It unfortunately has a really high
access latency, but it can
peak at about 562.5 megabytes per second.
It literally stores everything, because the
N64 uses a Unified Memory Architecture,
and it can be expanded to 8MB megabytes
using an expansion pack,
which you can slot into your N64.
The RCP: it's a magical black box
made by Silicon Graphics.
It does pretty much everything
that's related to what will
come out of your TV, so that includes
audio, graphics...
It can also do I/O and
a bunch of other things
It runs parallel to the CPU at
62.5 megahertz,
has absolutely no documentation
whatsoever, because Nintendo was afraid
that competitors would steal
their design,
and it's split into three main parts
parts, which I'll only be focusing on
two of them, which is:
the Reality Display Processor,
and the Reality Signal Processor.
RDP/RSP for short.
The I/O isn't really super important for
the programmer,
so I'm not gonna really focus on it.
The first part, the
Reality Display Processor,
it is a fixed-pipeline
rasterizer + shader.
It can do Z-buffering, mipmapping,
anti-aliasing, pretty much all sorts of
cool high-end stuff, that was
kinda rare at the time.
It has a 4 kilobyte instruction cache,
sorry I mean it has a 4KB texture cache.
Which is really small, we'll get
into that in a bit...
And unfortunately, it needs to be
manually synced,
so anytime that you change
anything on RDP, you need to
manually call a pipeline sync command.
It can reach 640x480, although
typically games ran at 320x240,
because most games were fillrate
limited, not really geometry limited.
So there's people who try to market
CPU overclocking things for the N64,
but that's really stupid because it
won't like help in 90% of the cases.
And the RDP doesn't support shaders,
because it's fixed pipeline,
but it does let you do some
cool stuff with the
Color Combiner and Blender,
which we'll get into in a little bit.
The Reality Signal Processor is a
vector processor.
It can control many different
things in the RDP,
and you can do many other things by
programming it with microcode.
With microcode, you can do graphics,
audio, you can have it decompress assets,
you can even get video running off
of it, if you want.
It is not great for audio, it does 16-bit
audio, but it can do 48 kilohertz stereo.
And it uses fixed point numbers for
best performance. I believe it also has
some floating point operation stuff
there, but frankly just stick to
fixed point numbers...
So, putting all that together, your
hardware looks a little something
like this:
The RCP is at the center and
that's a great thing because
the RCP is the fastest runni-
...
Yeah I really don't know
what they were thinking...
I mean I get *why* it's
at the center
because, you know, RAM stores
everything that you need for drawing,
so the RCP needs to have access
to it all the time.
Giving DMA to it was smart,
but cheaping out on the clock rate
was kind of leaving the rest of the
system at its mercy...
So like, remember that 500 megabyte
per second theoretical RAM peak?
HA!
Yeah, with the RCP running at
60 megahertz, you're gonna be
lucky if you even manage half of that,
especially with half of your
direct memory addressing being
occupied by audio processing.
I mean, I'm being a little bit evil here,
because the N64 was incredibly
tightly designed, after all, the RCP
was made from scratch by
Silicon Graphics for the console.
But obviously, it came at a little bit
of a cost to developers,
Especially because the RCP has
absolutely no documentation.
So you can kind of start to see what
Genyo Takeda was talking about.
So, the N64 uses cartridges.
This was a GREAT idea,
because cartridges are
incredibly fast, you don't really have
any loading screens like you would on
the *stupid* PlayStation 1
(N64 Forever)
And you can even almost stream data
from it.
You can fit in extra hardware
on the cartridges.
Usually cartridges came with 4
Kilobit saves.
You can also have a real-time clock!
One of the games on the N64
has a real-time clock built into
the cartridge.
And there's even a cartridge with
a modem slot in it, so you can plat online.
Now, the cartridges were also a TERRIBLE,
terrible idea, because cartridges are
quite expensive to make especially
compared to pressing some CDs.
Adding in more assets to your game
will balloon the cartridge's cost.
Every little megabyte was really
important at the time.
I only know two games on the Nintendo 64
that are 64 megabytes in size.
Those are: Conker's Bad Fur Day
and Resident Evil 2.
Conker's Bad Fur Day has fully
voice acted cutscenes,
while Resident Evil 2 has full motion
video.
Hence, why they're so big...
Technically, the CPU can address
250 megabytes, and recent discussions
have actually figured out that it can
do almost 2000 megabytes,
but this hasn't properly been
physically tested so
don't take my word on that yet...
But, with a cartridge with
custom hardware on it, you can
implement some sort of like bank switching
thing, and well, there your memory is
pretty much infinite.
[Audience Member]
That's cheating!
[Buu342]
Yeah well,
it's extra hardware so, y'know?
The SNES, they had extra sound chips
on some of their cartridges,
which is pretty cool, and the NES too,
I believe...
So, you're a brand new game dev,
and you want to try developing for
this Ultra 64 thing that Nintendo's
been talking about at E3.
Well, let me give you some pointers as to
why you should become a Nintendo partner.
Not only do you have a direct line of
support with Nintendo,
which also has Q+A's and developer
news, so you can stay updated on
all the Nintendo 64 things.
[Audience Member]
Is it still active?
[Buu342]
No, you wish!
It's compatible with that
Silicon Graphics Indy or Onyx,
if your office happens to have
one of those lying around...
And you get to play around with
all sorts of really fun hardware
which was relatively cheap at the time.
So, lets go over them!
The official Silicon Graphics setup,
as you can see over here.
A Silicon Graphics Indy, which was
the cheaper workstation that could
do N64 stuff, would be priced
around 5000 US Dollars.
Then, you could buy a special
board that you would fit into your Indy.
And, obviously, a tall cartridge with a
debugger port on the top of it.
You'd get a license for something like
MultiGen, which would work on
your Silicon Graphics. And, in total,
you pay about 17,500 dollars
for working on N64 stuff.
Later on, Nintendo did provide some
PC tools, because PCs were
a bit more common and, y'know,
everyone kinda had a PC eventually.
You instead you get a different
emulator and debugger that
Nintendo provides. You will need
some extra hardware for developing
sound stuff, so you'd have to buy the
SoundTools.
And you can get a license for something
like 3DS Max for 4,000 bucks.
A bit cheaper than stuff for
Silicon Graphics machines...
Alternatively, a company called Bung
released something called the Doctor V64,
And you could essentially run
homebrew off of it.
So you could you could get one
of those for about 450 dollars.
You will need a copy of any N64 game so
you can bypass the system's lockout chip.
And since we're trying to be as cheap
as possible, for an animation program
that would work on Windows 95,
I would recommend something like Anim8or.
But, nowadays we don't need to worry
about all this sort of old stuff...
So in a more modern setup, you
would buy a flashcart for about 200 bucks.
You can get a copy of Blender for
literally free, and for audio development
you can use something like
OpenMPT or Anvil Studio
for making MIDI stuff.
So, it's much easier to get into N64
development now, than it was before.
Speaking of SDKs, since you
actually wanna write software,
you're gonna need an SDK, and
there's two main reliable options
for N64. You have "libultra" which
was the official Nintendo 64
development SDK, made by
Nintendo. You get them in disks,
something a little bit like this:
Nowadays you can only really get
them from company liquidation auctions,
or you know you know someone who
happens to have a copy of them.
They'll work on Windows 95 or XP
out of the box, but you can
pretty much get them running on any
modern system using something like
DOSBox, Wine, WSL... We now have something
called the Modern SDK, which you can
pretty much get N64 stuff running
out of the box without any caveats.
Alternatively, you have something like
"libdragon", which is completely
open source.
But, it unfortunately only supports 2d...
This is changing very soon though!
They're making great progress on 3d
microcode.
It will work on pretty much any modern
system, and you can even get it on
something like Docker, if you prefer that.
And it is much, much easier to use
because the libdragon doesn't really
expose much of the operating system
to the developers.
For flashcarts, I know I've already
said this, but
get
get a
get a damn
get a damn flashcart.
Like, really. Yes.
With USB.
Like, I know it costs a little bit, but
it will save you a lot of frustration.
Not all of it, but some of it!
I personally recommend a 64Drive,
it's what I have over here.
It has a USB slot, an SD card slot,
and, a little clicky button!
Doesn't do anything!
You can make it programmed
to do stuff though!
The 64Drive was made by someone
called marshallh. He is a great guy,
and he's done *a lot* for the Nintendo 64
community, so I really recommend
getting a 64Drive.
But unfortunately, it's impossible! Because
as of making this presentation,
there have been a lot of
production issues, they're still being
kind of resolved... So you won't be
able to get a 64Drive for a little bit...
The other commercial option is
the EverDrive X7, although
you can get a 3.0 second handed.
It has a slightly slower USB, during
some of my testing, to upload a
64 megabyte ROM, it took almost
an entire minute...
It's not great... But it will work just as
well.
Alternatively, if you prefer to build
a flashcart yourself, you have something
like SummerCart 64, which is completely
open source!
I am going to shill a little bit, but
I've made a multi-platform
tool and library called UNFLoader.
It supports all three of the flashcarts
that I've mentioned in the presentation,
and it also works on both
libultra and libdragon. Use it!
It's probably going to be quite handy.
Especially for projects where you have
many different people with
different hardware. Like this, you
don't need to worry about your
USB code only working for
a specific cartridge.
And one of the main reasons you really
need to get a cartridge is because
you cannot trust Nintendo 64
emulators. Like, at all...
Not even CEN64, which is *the*
cycle accurate emulator.
There's not a single emulator that
emulates properly the Video Interface.
I'm not just talking about like:
"oh this pixel looks slightly off",
No, I'm talking about like more of
its actual quirks.
Developing without a flashcart is almost
impossible because if your game
is running on an emulator, there's no
guarantee that it will work on
the actual hardware.
So, y'know, if your game only works on
an emulator, you haven't really made a
Nintendo 64 game, you've made a PC game
with extra steps...
For programming, you pretty much develop
almost entirely in C.
You can use a little bit of C++. It was
seldomly use at the time because the
compilers weren't great.
There's one game-
[Audience Member]
Not even today?
[Buu342]
Today you can still use it.
I'll get to that in a second.
There was one commercial game, that I
know of, I'm sure there was a few others,
that use C++ for a few things.
One of them was Kirby64.
Just really, if you want to use C++
nowadays, don't rely on things like STL or-
[Audience Member]
No STL?
[Buu342]
Yeah no STL. A lot of that bloat...
I'm sorry...
[Audience Member]
Bloat?
[Buu342]
No. You can't.
You can develop stuff in assembly,
it's not required nor recommended
for an entire game.
But you can do it if you want to write
some super optimized functions.
Especially because official support
was really poor.
But nowadays you have something like
BASS, armips, and GAS
that you can use your
assemblers of choice.
If you are part of the cults, you
can also use Rust or Zig.
Zig quite recently people have
gotten compilers for those
languages working on the N64.
Just don't expect much
community support or many examples for
that stuff.
For other development tools, I know
this is a bit of a point of contention, but
most of the stuff, you're gonna have
to DIY. The official old tools are
kind of hard to find, or useless
without the special hardware.
For both SDK's, you'll pretty much
write most of your tools, or rely on
community made ones. Luckily, tools have
grown since I originally joined in 2018
(not just thanks to me obviously).
For instance, you want to get
animated models on the N64? Well,
you had to write your own tool and
plugin, or use Super Mario 64's code,
which was recently reverse engineered.
The other option was to grab something
like SoftImage 3D,
and I would not recommend it. It will
tear your hair out-
[Audience Member]
In regards to the reverse engineering
of Super Mario 64. Was that legal?
[Buu342]
Sorry?
[Audience Member]
[Buu342]
I am not a lawyer.
Well, it's still up today, the repository.
The repository's still up, so, y'know?
Nintendo hasn't done anything about it
yet.
Where was I?
Yeah, so, you could grab a copy of
something like SoftImage 3D, and
tear your hair out with the horrible,
horrible controls...
There was a lot of tools for static models,
but nothing really for animated models.
But recently, just this, month we had
three new tools released for Blender
That allows you to have different types
of animated models.
One of them I released, obviously.
For sound, you have things like...
libdragon recently got an XM player
that's microcode assisted, that's
pretty, pretty cool.
libultra also has a bunch of sound
tools, but they're mostly command line
based, so they're not really friendly for
artists who aren't super familiar
with that sort of stuff.
Alternatively, you can use the official
SoundTools...
I mean, they're powerful, but they're
really, really annoying to use without
the official hardware. You have to
jump through a bunch of hoops.
I intend on tackling audio development
a bit later in the future.
If you ever need anything N64
development related, just go to
https://n64.dev
It has all of your resources there,
it's community run, and it's still
updated. But, don't expect to find
something like Unity for N64,
where you can just drag assets
and compile a game. That not
gonna happen.
Ok so, we got the boring stuff,
out of the way, let's actually
talk about making games for the
Nintendo64.
I mostly use libultra, but I have
consulted a little bit with the
libdragon developers, so this section
should be relevant to both people.
The Nintendo 64 provides a very small
kernel. Everything is pretty much
done by you, tailored specifically
for your game. libdragon handles
a lot of the OS overhead. Heck, if you,
work with libdragon, you don't even
need to worry about what a thread is.
With libultra, you need to write
the OS yourself. You can alternatively
use Nintendo's Nusys, which was
something that they provided
later on which helps get rid of a lot of
the boilerplate when you're starting
your project.
Regardless of what route you decide to
take, there's no harm in understanding
the driving forces behind what actually
makes the machine tick.
So, the N64's CPU is a single core CPU,
threading is handled entirely by you.
libultra exposes a preemptive
scheduler, where threads are given
priorities. They only yield to the next
highest priority when choose to do so.
However, a thread can be interrupted
by the hardware and it can be switched
to another thread.
Essentially, the way that it works is:
the CPU gives the RCP things to do,
like for instance, render a frame,
and the RCP does that on its own.
The CPU then continues doing
whatever it wants.
Then, when the RCP finishes, it will
generate an interrupt, and the CPU will
then process whatever happened, and give
the RCP another task.
It's essentially just a back and forth
like that.
Threads can communicate between
each other's using messages.
you'd probably want to have a message
queue so that you can deal with
stuff later if it's not super important.
Threads can be paused at any time to,
for instance, want this thread to only
run as soon as it receives a message
or a specific interrupt/event, like if
your game crashes. You can have a
thread only run when that happens.
There are no threads in libdragon,
because libdragon uses an asynchronous
programming paradigm, but you can
choose to write an interrupt handler for
when, like, tasks finish, so that you can
schedule more.
Though libdragon is intending to
change this with a recent PR for a
kernel rewrite, so you can look
forward to that.
So, speaking of microcode since I've
mentioned microcode a little bit.
When you're making RSP tasks
from the CPU, you can choose what
microcode to execute. microcode is
usually linked in the ROM itself as
a binary blob.
There's a few options for microcode I'll
go over some of them quite briefly.
You have F3DEX, which is the 3D
microcode of choice.
Originally the microcode was called Fast3D,
and it was written by Silicon Graphics.
Although, it was not very good because
Silicon Graphics designed it to render
high quality triangles, which is not a
great idea for games....
Where y'know, you need to
run things fast...
Eventually, Nintendo wrote the
F3DEX series and they replaced the
Fast3D microcode.
For open source stuff, you have
something called ugfx, which came
out quite recently. It came out last
month!
But, it is currently having a complete
API rewrite. So if you choose to use it
now, you do need to be aware that
in the future, everything will be broken.
There's also an unfinished, but very
promising looking, 3D microcode: libhfx.
For 2D stuff, you have S2DEX, but
you can also just use F3DEX
microcode for your 2D rendering stuff.
So, like that, you don't need to be
swapping out
microcode between tasks, you can just
use F3DEX for that.
libdragon doesn't have any 2D
microcode, because it generates the
commands on the CPU and issues them
directly to the RDP.
Audio. For audio, you have something
like naudio, which is the Nintendo
audio microcode. And libdragon now
recently got something called the
RSP mixer.
I'll cover a little bit of audio
a little bit later.
If you're so inclined, you also have
microcode for video decoding.
Nintendo provided something called
HVQM, but we recently got something
which allows you to use H264, which is
very, very good and runs very very well.
There were some developers like Rare and
Factor 5, that Nintendo gave them the
source code for microcode and the very,
very bad documentation that the
source code had.
And these two companies went through
hell to write really good microcode to make
their games look fantastic. I mean, Conker
almost looks like something that would
run on the GameCube, it's very impressive
how much work they put into that.
[Audience Member]
Has someone ported Bad Apple to it?
[Buu342]
Yes! Someone has ported Bad Apple to it...
Obviously!
I have absolutely no experience writing
microcode, but it is easier to write
microcode nowadays, because there's
been a lot of hard work into getting
an interactive RSP disassembler
called r64emu.
Like, the developers at the time WISH
they had something as good as that.
So, remember how I mentioned that
memory that the N64 uses a sort of
unified memory architecture?
Well, you see, the RCP has really, really
small registers. Like, it only has a
four kilobyte instruction cache. It's
very very tiny... So if you have large
microcode, you need to load it in
as parts.
So pretty much everything will be
stored in RAM, 4 megabytes sounds
like it's a lot, but that space is being
contested by everything, like your
framebuffer and Z-buffer, and obviously
the framebuffer and Z-Buffer's sizes
will depend on your region. Typically on
NTSC systems, the buffers were 320x240
(320x288 if you're on PAL).
It does support some other weirder
resolutions if you really have to.
Typically you'd have two framebuffers,
so you can do double buffering for a
small framerate boost. So if you do
the math, that's about 300 kilobytes
for two framebuffers. It's double that
if you're using a 32-Bit color depth,
on top of the 150 that's being used by
the Z-buffer, so that's half a meg
gone, like that.
Although you, can cheat for PAL, because
the video interface lets you stretch the
Y scale for each horizontal scanline, while
still using an NTSC sized framebuffer.
But, it will make your stuff look
a little blurry on PAL and will make
me cry a lot.
RAM is made of 1 megabyte banks,
so putting both frame buffers in different
banks will improve the performance.
Because each time that you
write or read to a bank, you have to wait
for the operation to finish before the
same bank can be accessed again.
The RAM interface supports multiple
banks at once, that allows you to read
from different banks while one is
being used.
Remember, you have full control of the
memory layout, so alternate your data
between the banks, it helps a lot.
I was going to give an example of this
in practice, but because we are on an
emulator it, won't really matter.
The idea here is that this first scene
is being rendered with the framebuffers
in separate banks, and then the second
scene is then being rendered with the
frambuffers all in the same bank. And
you would see that this one would
run a little bit worse.
The time up there is in milliseconds.
[Audience Member]
That's in milliseconds?
[Buu342]
Uh yeah, roughly.
So speaking of memory management, the
bootcode will copy the very first
megabyte from ROM, and it will
execute it.
There is absolutely no way to change
this without modifying the bootcode itself,
which is not trivial for a bunch of reasons
that I'm not going to get into here.
Essentially, this means, don't put
your data in your code segment or
you'll very quickly surpass this limit.
The cartridge is very fast, so you can load
assets from it as your game is running.
If you DO happen to hit that one
megabyte limit, you can apply some
classic operating system techniques to
work around it.
So, overlays, which is, you essentially
say "this" block of code occupies
"this" position in memory, and
"this other" block of code ALSO
occupies the exact same place in
memory, but only one block of code
will ever be active at a time, so
you can swap them out.
Alternatively, you can use something like
relocatable modules, where it's the
exact same thing, where you have
a block of code,
you get it from memory, and you
just place it somewhere.
But the thing about relocatable modules
is that the pointers are corrected for
wherever you put it in RAM, so you're not
forced to overlay it with the other code.
So you can have multiple different
things running at once.
Since we're talking about getting stuff
from ROM, you're essentially talking about
a filesystem. The N64 doesn't force any
structure for your filesystem, so just
do whatever you want with memory.
libdragon has its own filesystem that
you might find quite handy.
Speaking of memory management,
it's important to mention that the CPU
runs in kernel mode, so there's a bit
of legwork that you need to do.
The CPU usually runs in KSEG0's address
space, it's direct memory mapped, cached.
While the RCP expects the addresses that
you give it to be physical addresses.
So you do need to manually correct that.
Because the CPU transparently caches
data accesses on the onboard data cache,
when you DMA stuff, to y'know, get assets
from ROM, the data is held in the cache
until the cache line is written back,
usually because a cache miss occurs
which requires the same cache line.
Because they will no longer agree
on the contents of the cache, you'll
need to manually writeback the
data cache or invalidate it when you have
more recent data in your physical memory.
Y'know, it's some extra annoying steps
that the developers had to worry about
at the time.
Okay so, let's talk a little bit about
graphics. This section is when it's
it's going to get a little dense, so give
me a sec.
Okay so, first and foremost, this
question gets asked a lot but
no, the Nintendo 64 does NOT use
OpenGL.
Yes, the OpenGL API was written by
Silicon Graphics,
and at the time, their machines were
working with their proprietary IRIS GL,
but the N64 uses its own thing. We
sometimes call it N64GL
Not an official name!
That's not saying that knowing stuff about
OpenGL is useless, it is not, it will help
you, especially the main concepts like
matrix calculations, lighting,
but you know there's a lot of
small differences in the details.
Regardless, if you do happen to have a copy
of the "OpenGL Superbible: First Edition",
This is a great book, you want to get
resources essentially for the 1.0
iterations of OpenGL, the ones that use
display lists.
It's going to be quite a useful resource
for you.
So, I just mentioned the N64 uses
display lists, because the graphics cards
at the time were mostly fixed
function pipelines.
you can dynamically create display lists
as your application is running, or you
have some static pre-made display
lists for static data, like your
character models, the vertices aren't
really going to change, so you
don't need to generate those dynamically.
In OpenGL, you have something called the
post transform cache, which is a small
memory buffer where you put in
vertices when they're being processed,
but not yet rendered.
The N64 has an explicitly managed
version of this, with the size of the
cache itself depending on which
microcode you're using.
The tricky part about this is that
the vertices you load need to be
in contiguous order. So, for instance,
if you have a vertex cache size of
32, you can't selectively load vertex
number 4 and then load vertex 64.
You can't do that, you have to order your
vertices so that you know they fit in
blocks together.
Or, if you can't do that, then you
need to duplicate your vertices.
there's quite a few algorithms for this,
like Tipsify, or Forsyth, but it's
relatively easy to write your own.
Preventing cache misses when you're
loading your vertices is relatively easy,
and it's a great way to improve your
performance, even though you don't
need to spend years trying to improve
the algorithm, because it's going
to a point where you're going to be
fillrate limited so... It won't really
matter too much.
The N64's graphics API provides a 10
element modeling matrix stack, like you'd
kinda expect any modern graphics API
to have, the catch is that the matrix
stacking is done when the RSP is processing
the display list tasks themselves, so
you can't just call a matrix push operation
and then reuse that matrix for
something else with the CPU. You have to
keep that matrix loaded in memory otherwise
you're you're gonna run into
some problems...
It also supports vertex colors, which
are used to great extent in a lot of
titles, however be aware that you
can't actually mix vertex colors
and lighting, because the lighting is
actually faked. It's modifying the
vertex colors directly.
You can, however, mix primitive colors
with lighting, you just can't mix the
individual vertex colors.
The largest point of contention for most
people with the system is that the
texture memory is tiny, it's
4 kilobytes...
For reference, if you have an 32-Bit color
image,
this is the size of the texture
that you can fit in that memory.
[Audience Member]
Just one question, why did they end up
making the texture memory so small?
[Buu342]
Probably cost saving measures, you'd
have to ask a Silicon Graphics engineer.
This joke would have been funnier on
the console because this would have
looked a little bit smaller.
For reference, this is a 32x32 pixel
image.
If you're using mipmapping, that's
going to get even smaller, that's
gonna be half of that...
There is no way to bypass this
limitation, because it needs the
textures to be loaded into texture
memory for the RDP to use them.
The best thing that you can do to
render high quality textures is to
either reduce the bit depth of the
texture itself, like for instance this
texture doesn't use any alpha so I can
forego the alpha bits completely,
or you can instead use something like
4-Bit black and white textures,
and then just use vertex colors to
color your texture. Like that, you
can almost fit a 128x128 texture in it.
Or the other choice is to chunk your
images and load them bit by bit.
If you're doing this for a model, you'll
need to increase the number of triangles
on the model itself.
So I mentioned the Color Combiner. This
is the closest thing that you're going
to have to a fragment shader.
The Color Combiner is essentially a
very, very simple equation.
It's:
(a - b)*c + d
These variables, you can essentially
fit from a few different sources.
So you can fit in the texture color, the
vertex color, you can fit in noise,
primitive color, the ambient color, or
just a 1 or a 0.
The color combiner is also used for
alpha, and it uses the exact same equation.
the cool thing about the color combiner is
that you can do it in two different passes.
So, you can calculate a specific color
in one pass, and then use the
value that you calculated as a variable
in your second pass.
This will obviously be slower, since each
pixel now needs to be processed twice
with the Color Combiner.
And this will even allow you to do three
color multiplications, because this formula
only lets you do two color multiplications
if you do it in a single pass.
Let me demonstrate.
So over here I have everything
set to 0, so we just have a black
square.
Or, I can change "d" to-
Sorry, I didn't mean to hit that button...
I can change "d" to instead be a 1, and
now it's pure white, which is probably
going to be very, very difficult to see.
We can replace "d" instead to use the
vertex color, or we can have it with
the texture color.
You can replace "a" with the vertex
color, and "c" with the texture color,
and you can multiply them.
It's a little bit hard to see over here
on the projector, sorry about that
guys. Should be fine on the stream...
I hope...
You can also change "a" to be noise.
Noise only seems to work on "a", I
can't really get it to work on the
other variables, I'm not sure why...
And then replace "c" with the vertex
color, and "d" with the texel color-
Whoops, I keep pressing the wrong button...
And you're gonna get something that looks
a little bit like this. And obviously, if
you wanna do something a little bit
more fancy, you can mix in ambient
color by doing it in a second pass. So
I've replaced "a" with the combined result
of the first pass and then multiplied
all of that by the ambient color.
Okay, now we can actually go to this
slide...
The Blender, it essentially combines the
calculated value from the Color Combiner,
and it blends it with the ones in the
framebuffer. It also does the
anti-aliasing and Z-buffering.
It's essentially what shades the final
pixel.
I didn't demonstrate this in the
previous slide, but the Color Combiner
and the Blender kind of need to work
together for the output to be correct.
The Blender is a pretty complex beast,
it has more than one equation for
calculating which pixel gets outputted.
Like, there's a specific formula
if you want to use fog.
The N64 manual has this really big
matrix that shows all the different
sources that you can use for the
Blender and what they will do.
I'm not really gonna get into the
Blender because I don't wanna
take too much time, I only have an hour, so
we're not gonna really talk about it much.
Just read the manual, it'll cover it
a lot better than I could.
Okay so, model animations. It helps to
have your models animated to make your
game look a little bit more interesting.
But the fact that the Nintendo 64
doesn't really provide any ways to
easily do this, any built-in ways, it's a
bit overwhelming for newcomers who've
never had to implement something
like a skinning system before.
The most common used system by the
the games on the N64 was something that
we call the "sausage link" system, although
I'm not sure if there's an official name
for this? But I doubt it sounds as cool as
"sausage links". Essentially, remember
that little animated model I made
for the intro?
It's made of a bunch of separate
segments, and they're really easy to
manipulate individually by a matrix.
And it's relatively lightweight in
terms of memory, because you only
need to store the final position,
rotation, and scale values for each
keyframe of the animation.
And you can use the CPU to lerp
between the different frames.
The RSP is the one that's doing all the
vertex transformations, so your CPU
is free to do other things.
You can also have fully skinned models
like you would have on a modern game.
One of the best ways to do this is by
storing multiple copies of your model,
just transformed frame by frame, and then
loading them in every frame.
Remember that the DMA is relatively fast,
so you can do this in realtime.
You can also take a hybrid approach,
saving memory in your ROM by cutting
the in between frames and linearly
interpolating on the CPU. This will
obviously be very heavy as the
number of vertices increases,
so at that point you might as well
implement a full, proper skeleton system.
There's no microcode for skinned models
unfortunately, but it is theoretically
possible, and would be a much smarter
solution than doing it purely on the CPU.
A relatively cool trick for skinned meshes
is the fact that when you load vertices
into the vertex cache, they're transformed
by the current matrix that's in the stack.
This means that if you're careful with
how you load your vertices, you can
effectively fake skinned meshes.
The idea is that you load
one bone's worth of vertices, probably
want to ensure that you load the vertices
that's at the tail of the bone last,
then you push the matrix for the next bone,
and you load its corresponding vertices.
You want to load those vertices at an
offset so that you don't overwrite
the previous ones. So the new vertices will
be transformed but the old ones won't be.
And then, you simply just need to
render an extra triangle in between these,
in the connecting vertices, and here you
go, here's a fake skinned thing.
There aren't any tools that let you do
this automatically, I did this by hand.
And this method won't really work well
for meshes that have UV coordinates, since
getting the textures to work right on
this is gonna be a little tricky.
The other caveat is that obviously this
system only supports skinned models
with vertices of weight 1 or 0, you won't
be able to have any in between weights.
[Buu342]
Question?
[psenough]
Question from the audience.
[Buu342]
Yes?
[psenough]
What was the main reason for
making the models as sausage links? Is
there an aesthetic reason behind it?
It's how I explained, it's because you
can just load in a chunk of the model
and have the RSP do all the
vertex transformations, freeing up
the CPU to do other stuff. It was just
much easier for the CPU since everything's
being done by the RSP. The RSP is a
vector processor, it's fast, it can do it.
So, audio development...
Audio development largely
depends on the kind of microcode
that you're using, because the N64
doesn't really have a dedicated audio
chip, it's done in the RSP.
It's not locked to specific waveforms,
like the NES was, instead you just have
a 16-Bit audio buffer somewhere in
RAM that you can just, with the
combined effort of the CPU and RSP,
you just write waveform data into.
Or you can just write it directly with
the CPU, if you really want to.
Because the PAL and NTSC N64s run at
different clock rates, the audio will sound
a little bit different between the
two regions, so you will need to
adjust the audio between those two regions.
It's important that you test on both
systems.
It's also important that you give your
audio thread as much priority as possible,
otherwise you will get pops or clicks.
And audio pops and clicks are much more
noticeable than a dropped frame or
two. And much more annoying...
So it helps to write a scheduler that
lets you interleave audio and
graphics tasks properly.
Thankfully a lot of the hard audio work
has been done for you, so instead
you can just use one of the provided
libraries from your SDK of choice.
For libultra, you have the naudio
microcode, which was used by both
the Silicon Graphics' machine audio tools,
and the SoundTools on the PC.
The RSP is used essentially to
decompress the audio, apply effects,
generate music notes using MIDI from
sound banks that you can provide to it.
The MIDI's themselves don't really have
any channel limits, because in the end
everything just gets crushed into one
buffer, so that information will be
lost anyway...
libdragon recently got a new audio
microcode called RSP Mixer.
I believe that's the name that they
use for it. There's no fancy name for it.
Unlike the Nintendo microcode,
it's designed for XM modules and
mostly for uncompressed audio
samples like WAV files.
If you really don't care about
your ROM size, you can just store
and stream your audio uncompressed,
directly from the cartridge.
One highly popular method for
compressing is to store your sounds
sped up, and then slowing them down
in the RSP. Because, y'know, sped up
sounds are shorter, so obviously the
file size is going to be smaller.
Obviously, the faster you make the
sound, the worse it will sound stretched.
So, people have talked about
about MP3 playback. It's entirely
possible, I know that Conker's
Bad Fur Day uses MP3 for its
audio. When you start up the game,
it has like the little library copyright
stuff on it. MP3 is a bit heavier on
the CPU than something like MP2,
but there aren't really any public
microcode for either format, so you
have to make do, unfortunately.
[Audience Member]
Perfect Dark also uses MP3.
[Buu342]
Possibly yes, since it's also Rare.
They were by the same company.
So, putting all that information together,
you've coded your game and you've
made a terrible discovery!
It runs like absolute ass!
Yep! That's right, get used to it!
F-Zero X is the only commercial game on
the system that I know of that runs
at a near stable 60 frames per
second at all times.
I've mentioned it before, but most games
on the system are fillrate limited, so
you can use the CPU as much as
you want. To, y'know, help reduce
overdraw, you can clip out triangles.
Help out the RDP however you can.
I've also heard about people talking
about overclocking the CPU, but don't
do this, it's really stupid. There's no
benefit in doing so because 90% of
the games out there won't benefit
from it. It'll potentially even mess up
the timings, since games are designed
with the very specific timings of the
CPU, and it can even break the VI
or other things.
And obviously, it'll make the CPU run
hotter, which isn't a great idea because
the console is completely passively cooled.
One of the best ways to improve your
performance is to reduce texture loading.
There's someone who made Mario Kart 64
run 40% percent times faster by simply
just reducing texture loads. And by that,
I mean you load in the texture, and you
render everything that uses that
specific texture. And you won't
ever need to load it again. The text
that you're seeing here for this
presentation, I essentially have a big list
of all the different characters in memory,
split into chunks that will fit into
texture memory, and I do some
processing on the CPU. I create a
hash table, where I put in all the
specific letters that use a specific
texture, and like that I can just
render all of the letters at once
that use that specific texture.
You want to do this sort of stuff
as much as possible.
You'll also want to optimize your
drawing order. So, you'll want to draw
from front to back, because the
pixels that are drawn from behind
a triangle can be skipped early.
Also, an interesting tidbit, the Z-Buffer
is atrocious atrociously slow, but
not everything that you draw
requires it, so you can selectively
disable the Z-Buffer to
maximize your performance.
If you really want, you can even
toggle anti-aliasing between frames.
As in, like, render one frame with
anti-aliasing, render another frame
without it, and have it swap
between the two.
And the more obvious things, you can
use culling algorithms like
Binary Space Partitioning, or use
Level of Detail models.
I've mentioned it plenty before, but the
CPU bus is 32-Bits wide, so if
you have your data aligned to
prevent cache misses, that's a
great idea, and keep them in different
banks, that also helps.
And I know that using compiler
optimization sounds a bit obvious,
but Super Mario 64 shipped in debug
mode, and the performance is pretty
noticeable, especially in the CPU
bottlenecked areas.
Also,
read the manual.
Like, really do it.
Yeah, I know it's like 30 chapters
long, and its very dry, but there's
so much important stuff in it.
[psenough]
Didn't you say that there was
no documentation?
[Buu342]
Oh, that's for the RSP.
Yeah, for the RSP and the RDP, how
those things work internally, there's
no documentation for that, but
you do have like a big thick manual of
how to get stuff working, obviously,
otherwise you'd be screwed...
Okay so, to wrap up this presentation, I
want to talk a little bit about the
beginning, and the future of
Nintendo 64 homebrew development.
So if anyone follows Nintendo gaming
news, you might be aware that Nintendo
has a notoriously crappy attitude
for fan games. They've shut down
lots of projects that have a lot of
really hard work put into them...
I'd like to put your worries to rest
by mentioning the fact that Nintendo
historically has never gone after homebrew
games. It only acts on fan games,
because people are using their IP's and
characters without their permission.
Like I mentioned, the Super Mario 64
decompilation project, it's still up after
three years, because it contains no
game assets in its repository. You
need a copy of the game, and you
run it through some scripts, and it
will generate those assets for you.
Originally, in 1997 a man by- er, I
think it's a man...
SOMEONE by the name of ACTRAiSER
registers a little website
called https://dextrose.com to collect
information about backup devices for
the Nintendo 64. It quickly became a place
where people gathered to discuss and
develop Nintendo 64 homebrew.
Unfortunately though, most of this
website has been lost to time, but
it can still be partially surfed
through the web archive. However,
in 1998, Dextrose, in collaboration
with Bung Enterprises, the guys who
made that Dr. V64 that I mentioned before.
They announced something called:
Presence of Mind. It was the first
Nintendo 64 demo competition.
And the winners could take in some
cool sponsored hardware by Bung, and
every competitor even got a free T-shirt.
There's a demo for Presence of Mind
that's literally just called
The T-shirt demo.
The demo essentially says "we couldn't
make anything in time, but we heard
we'd get a free T-shirt, so here's
something".
There was a second and final
Presence of Mind in 1998.
During this time frame, the system was
pretty hot, so we saw a lot of releases,
a lot of demos, intros, and homebrew,
which is pretty cool.
In 1999, an SGI employee leaks internal
documents containing Verilog code and
a lot of really juicy details called:
The Oman Archives.
[Audience Member]
The Oman Archives?
[Buu342]
T̷̨̝̤̦͎͂̈́̅̎̈́ḩ̴͉̻͈̦͈͖̱̩̯͖̥͉̖́̈́̋̌͑͐͆̏̌̈͛̀͋͝é̴̺̝̗̰͖̗̪̹̦̳͎̹̾̆̂̉̈́̉͊̚͠ ̷̣̱̍͑̋̑̐͗̀̅̀̚͝͝O̷̞̳̘͖͓̗̫̦͈̅͠m̵̺͙̞̍̍̄̏̈̅̔̋̈͌͌͝ă̴̦̦͎̖̰͓͇̠̫̮̑̇̑͗̒̓͌̀̈̈́͘n̵̡̛͚̱̫͖͚̮̱̈́̒̉̏͒͝͝͝ͅ ̸̛̩͖̳̩̉̄̈́̓̌̓́͋̌͆͝͝͝Ä̶̧͇̘͉̫̗̲̘͙͚̺͜ͅͅŗ̴̬̗̻̘͕̳̟̳͍̻͖̤̾̿̒̾̋͜͜c̵̳͈͕͙̠̹̑̂̂͋̀̅̀͆͝h̸̢̛̼̻̑̍̌̎̿̚i̴̡̤͕̠̹͚̥̯̎͆̓̈́̑̔̿̋̉̂͜v̷̧͚͕̩̮̭̰͓̬̥̞͈̅̇̏͘͝ȩ̴̨̢̺͚̦̝͔͇͈͔̍̀̿̉̕͠͝s̸̰̖̯̣̲̥͈̻̭͈̹͚̠̆͌̆̕
This has unfortunately tainted the N64
scene, and it has never been the same
since. It's forbidden knowledge, and some
emulator developers have used them.
They shouldn't have...
And a lot of that information has
unfortunately propagated through
the rest of the scene since.
Eventually though, Project64 is released
in 2001 and it rises above the rest as
one of the best Nintendo 64
emulators at the time.
Eventually though, it's time for the
new console generation, so the Nintendo 64
is discontinued in 2002, and at this point,
the interest in the system starts to
and it's really only kept alive by a
small handful of users, mostly who
are either emulator developers, hackers who
are working to translate the Japanese only
games to English, or just people interested
in taking the system apart and figuring
it out bit by bit.
The emulation scene unfortunately
also saw quite a bit of infighting and
elitism, which kind of still lingers to
this day. It's a bit unfortunate...
[Audience Member]
What kind of fighting?
[Buu342]
I really don't want to get into the drama.
You can you can probably just search
Project64 on Wikipedia and there's a
section called "controversy". Y'know,
it's always a good Wikipedia article
when it has that section in it.
[Audience Member]
What about high level emulation?
Did that die off?
[Buu342]
So, there was a high level emulator soon
after The Oman Archives which had to be
discontinued because-
[Audience Member]
UltraHLE?
Was it UltraHLE?
[Buu342]
Yes, UltraHLE! I don't know if that was
the one that used part of the Oman
documentation, I'm a little bit hazy
in that history, unfortunately...
[Audience Member]
I remember that when it was released
it was quite good.
[Buu342]
Yes! It was very, very good for its time.
So now we're seeing a bit of a renaissance.
Collectors have gotten ahold of the
original development hardware and
disks. We saw the release of alt-libn64
in 2008, which eventually merged with
libdragon in 2010. There was a lot of
collaborative work from users to write
these free and open source libraries.
And, of note, in 2011 marshallh, who made
my little cartridge, he released the
MGC Demo, which was the first N64
demo in a long time. They also
managed to fully reverse engineer the
CIC, which was the lockout chip on the
system, and that eventually brought
the release of the 64Drive. It has
something called the UltraCIC, which is
an open source CIC re-implementation
that works on all sorts of CIC's. There's a
bunch of different CIC's and the UltraCIC
supports all of them.
Six years later, Discord happens,
and the N64brew Discord channel
is created, which I end up joining and
releasing my first homebrew project
in 2018.
I know it feels a little bit cheeky
putting one of my own projects in
a timeline of big occurrences, but before
my game, there wasn't really any properly
documented N64 game. No one
had really gone into such an extent
to make write-ups about how to make a
game, step by step. And that was one of
the things that I did with my project.
I promise one day I will finish that
documentation. I know I'm like 2 years
behind, but-
[Audience Member]
Is that online yet?
[Buu342]
Yes it's online, obviously.
[psenough]
Just unfinished, right?
[Buu342]
It's just unfinished, but yes,
If you search up Pyoro64, which is the
name of the project, you will find
those Google Docs.
Also worth noting-
Oh! Also, the Pyoro thing,
sometimes when I look at
other people's open source project,
I sometimes find a little bit of
Pyoro code in there, so it's a little
bit nice-
[Audience Member]
You mean they're copy pasting you code?
[Buu342]
It's like a line or 2, but I can see
from the comments that it came from my
ROM, so you know, people have found
those samples very useful.
Which is pretty good!
As I mentioned, Super Mario 64 was
decompiled in 2019... Well it was
decompiled before but it went public in
2019, and this completely exploded the
Super Mario hacks, and N64 hacks
scene in general.
Last year, N64brew hosted the very
first Nintendo64 homebrew competition.
We had a 1000 dollar prize pool, and that
competition happened 20 years after
the last Presence of Mind.
We also created the N64brew wiki,
which now kind of serves as a hub
for accurate hardware and software-
[Audience Member]
Is this recent?
[Buu342]
documentation. Yes, it's very recent.
A lot of the documentation that you
can find online is wrong, and we're trying
to correct that.
[Audience Member]
Like what?
[Buu342]
Lots of like, really finicky details,
because as I mentioned, we thought
the CPU could only address 250 megabytes,
turns out it can potentially address
more than that. But no one bothers
to update this stuff-
[Audience Member]
So it's for people who are
more into hardware?
[Buu342]
Yes, it's more for emulator-
There's a little bit of everything in
there. It's got stuff for emulator
developers but it also has a few guides
that I'm also helping write about
software development in general.
And in case you're wondering, yes, we're
hosting another game jam right now!
Although, it is unfortunately a little
bit late to sign up... And this year's
prize pool is instead going to charity
since we we want to try something
a little bit different.
This chart isn't really super
comprehensive, but I've tried
to the best of my ability to
ensure it's somewhat accurate.
the numbers over here-
I programmed a laser pointer!
Because I was expecting to have to show
this on the console.
[psenough]
Question. Is there a specific place
where you collect all the homebrew
releases?
[Buu342]
No... We we might do that with
the wiki. For now, we put up a GitHub
repository with all the game jam entries
from last year, and we're going to do the
same thing again.
There's a website called
https://n64squid.com, where
someone publishes articles about
all sorts of n64 homebrew.
There's a website called
http://nesworld.com, it also has a
big compilation of homebrew ROMs so
that's probably worth looking at...
So the numbers here in the Dextrose
years, are a little bit inflated,
because I've also included intros
and demos.
After dextrose-
[Audience Member]
But it's still homebrew, right?
[Buu342]
Yeah it's still homebrew, but most
people, when they think about
homebrew, they want to see games.
You had a lot of that in the
Dextrose years,
and less as time went on...
And I'm also not including hacks,
if we include hacks, this chart would
be much, much bigger.
We've had translation patches and
all sort of stuff throughout the years,
and I didn't include these in the chart.
It's not a super accurate chart, but it's
just to get a general idea...
You can see here that in 2017 we saw a
small uptick of homebrew, probably
because of N64brew, but things
started going a bit more public...
And then you can see in 2020 it suddenly
jumped up again with the game jam.
[psenough]
They were asking if it was because of
the pandemic? Like, everybody indoors had
a lot more time to hack at the N64?
It probably helped...
It definitely helped...
Okay, speaking of communities, if you like
IRC, you have #n64dev which is @ EFnet.
It's one of the oldest active communities,
it was around during the Dextrose days,
and it contains most of the old timers,
it has really knowledgeable folk there.
N64brew Discord is the kind of go-to place
for homebrew development specifically.
You also have Discord 64, you have
iQueBrew which is specifically for the
Chinese console of the Nintendo 64.
They had a Chinese version, yes.
[psenough]
What's the difference between the normal
and the Chinese version?
[Buu342]
I'm not sure because I-
[psenough]
It's Chinese!
[Buu342]
I don't own one...
The idea was that, because gaming
is super restricted in China,
Nintendo had to release it slightly
differently, not as a gaming console,
but as an entertainment thing instead.
Instead, it's called the iQue Player,
instead of the Nintendo64
And you also have a bunch of hacking
communities for very specific titles,
like Super Mario 64, Legend of Zelda,
Banjo, GoldenEye, etc...
And while it's not super active, if you
like Reddit, you also have the
r/n64homebrew subreddit.
Okay, well, that's everything!
Thanks for putting up with me.
If you ever need to get in touch,
I have a bunch of links up here, in
the places I've listed:
My email, my GitHub (where I
open source everything, including the
source code for this presentation,
because it IS a Nintendo64 ROM).
I have a YouTube channel, I sometimes
publish stuff there...
Whenever I feel like it...
And my Discord, if you ever
need to get in touch directly.
I'd like to give special thanks to
a bunch of people:
Rasky, Bigbass, Hazematman,
Meeq, and mikeryan, for
proofreading, correcting me, answering
questions, being helpful with
putting this presentation together.
There are a bunch of names that have
kept the N64 community alive
throughout the years. I'd spend ages
mentioning every single one, so here's a
few up on the screen. Not comprehensive,
at all!
N64brew has been a fantastic place that
has kept me there for over three years.
I highly recommend it!
And super thank you for that!
And obviously, Inércia for inviting me
to do this talk (and giving me
free food because I was doing the
seminar, thanks a lot, yeah).
Do you have time for questions?
[psenough]
Yeah, I'm asking on the chat if they
have any. There was one asking if it's
a proper old-school platform, or is it
still like "my console is a bit
outdated" sort of thing.
[Buu342]
I'd like to point out that the
PlayStation 3, at this point, is
considered retro.
The PlayStation 3 is over 10 years old,
so these systems are starting to get
quite old.
Oh yeah!
Here's a bunch of sources that you might
find useful.
The manual, read it!
[psenough]
Is there any effort to crack the
big black box in the middle?
[Buu342]
Yes! In fact, it's already been decapped.
But it's super complicated, so we
don't have like any... Yeah...
Any other questions?
[psenough]
Not right now.
So, everybody please-
There's a question!
What's the best n64 demo to watch?
[Buu342]
Okay so, for demos, I highly
recommend the MGC 2011 demo by marshallh.
And another really, really cool one is
called Nacho 64.
It does some really cool stuff, it has
a mirror in it!
[psenough]
I wonder if that was on purpose blackpawn,
that you asked that question.
Because blackpawn is getting this sort
of nacho theme going at Inércia, so I
wonder if that was related.
Curious...
[Buu342]
Those two are really, really impressive
looking, so I highly recommend those.
There's probably a few others, but I'm
not remembering right now from the top
of my head.
I would demonstrate them, if we
were running this presentation on
my console...
[psenough]
We... Does anyone know a cheap,
but reliable RCA to HDMI connector? If
you have one, please donate one to Buu,
he desperately needs one.
[Buu342]
I wanted to get a RetroTINK, but it's
40 bucks shipping to Portugal, and then
its 23% tax as soon as it arrives.
It hurts the wallet...
[psenough]
We have one more question, which was
highlighted here. Why did you get into
doing games for the N64?
What made you so interested?
[Buu342]
I owned the console.
[psenough]
Was it yours, or was it your parents'?
Because you're too young to have an N64!
[Buu342]
Wow, rude!
It was my cousins, actually they then
passed it onto my brother and I.
And now it's in my hands, since I do
homebrew development on it.
[psenough]
I think that's it, we don't have anything
else. Thank you so much Buu, that
was very interesting. Thank you so much!
Big round of applause!
And... We'll now have a short break to
prepare the next compos, which should be
15 minutes or something like that...
So yeah, stay tuned, and
we'll be right back!